<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | 8-bit Triangles]]></title>
  <link href="http://edrago.github.com/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://edrago.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-19T12:13:11-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://edrago.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Edson Drago]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing Mumble-Django under virtualenv and behind Nginx]]></title>
    <link href="http://edrago.github.com/2013/03/19-installing-mumble-django-behind-nginx.html"/>
    <updated>2013-03-19T11:20:00-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://edrago.github.com/2013/03/installing-mumble-django-behind-nginx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, I've been using murmur (the mumble server) on my VPS to host a server where
my friends can gather and talk freely for some time now. But none of then has
much expertise using technical computer programs, and I've been looking into a
front-end interface that would offer an easy way to some of then manage the
server, as I can't be online all the time.</p>

<p>After some research I ended up choosing Mumble-Django, because lately I've been
learning a little python and got interested in setting up the Django web-
framework, so there's my chance. The only problem was to set it up with Nginx,
as I found no tutorials, only for setting it with Apache or Lighthttp.</p>

<p>Without further ado, here's how I set it up on my VPS.</p>

<!-- More -->


<h3>Some disclaimer first</h3>

<p>I installed Mumble-Django on my server somewhat following the <em>manual
installation <a href="http://docs.mumble-django.org/en/installation.html#manual-installation">guide</a></em> from the official homepage, with some sparse
information helping to choose and learn how to use Gunicorn (Green Unicorn) WSGI
HTTP server built with python.<br/>
Other detail is that I'm doing all the installation and configuration in my VPS
with Debian 6.0 (Squeeze), some steps or details may change in other linux
distributions.
It's presumed that the reader has some basic knowledge of Linux and Nginx.</p>

<h2>Preparing the Environment</h2>

<p>First of all, I wanted to setup a secure and easy to handle Python environment.
The best solution I found was to use <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv">virtualenv</a> tool and run it from source
. So, let's get our hands with the initial setup.</p>

<p>First, download the source from the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/virtualenv">official page</a> on pypi wiki, uncompress
it and initialize the Env. Install the Mumble server (<em>murmur</em>) if you don't
have it already.
<code>
$ cd virtualenv
$ python virtualenv.py MD
$ aptitude install mumble-server # For Debian
</code></p>

<p>After that, use the <em>activate</em> script that's present on the bin folder of the
'MD' env so you can use the contents of env's <em>bin</em> as functions.<br/>
This isn't necessary, is just for convenience. Then install some dependencies.
<code>
$ source MD/bin/activate
  # Pil needs to be compiled in the process and might protest due to some
  # dependencies, I installed my distro package, but you could try to install
  # it with pip
  # i.e. pip install pil
$ aptitude install python-imaging # PIL
$ aptitude install python-simplejson # Same as PIL, 'pip install simplejson'
$ pip install django==1.2.3
$ pip install django-registration
$ pip install gunicorn
</code></p>

<p>Now, Mumble-Django needs some way to communicate with the murmur process and we
have two options. Using <a href="http://docs.mumble-django.org/en/connecting_murmur_to_dbus.html#en-connecting-dbus" title="Connecting Murmur to DBus">D-Bus</a> or <a href="http://docs.mumble-django.org/en/connecting_murmur_to_ice.html#en-connecting-ice" title="Making Murmur available via Ice">Ice</a>. I chose Ice, but you can pick
whatever method that you think it's best.</p>

<p>If you chose Ice you should install the <em>zeroc</em> library. In debian it comes in
the package <em>"python-zeroc-ice"</em>.</p>

<p>Because I am installing everything under virtualenv, it's necessary to provide
locally the libraries that I installed globally. So I link the necessary libs to
the <strong><em>lib</em></strong> folder in my Env.
<code>
$ ln -s /usr/share/pyshared/PIL lib/python2.6/PIL
$ ln -s /usr/share/pyshared/simplejson lib/python2.6/simplejson
$ ln -s /usr/share/pyshared/Ice* lib/python2.6/
$ ln -s /usr/lib/pyshared/python2.6/IcePy.so lib/python2.6/
</code></p>

<h2>Installing Mumble-Django</h2>

<p>The next step is to download the lastest version of the Mumble-Django from their
<a href="https://bitbucket.org/Svedrin/mumble-django/downloads">repository</a>. Go to "Tags" tab and download the version you want. I recommendto download from the <strong>Tag</strong> <em>stable</em>.<br/>
Then we download and uncompress it to our Env folder and do the initial setup.
<code>
$ wget https://bitbucket.org/Svedrin/mumble-django/get/stable.tar.gz
$ tar xvfz stable.tar.gz # rename the folder extracted to what you want
$ cd mumble-django/pyweb # I renamed mine to mumble-django
  # If you are using Ice, make sure that the path to Slice configured in settings.py
  # (variables SLICE and SLICEDIR) points to the correct location of Murmur.ice
  # file. If using Murmur 1.2.3 or higher you can just use getslice as below
$ python manage.py getslice
$ python manage.py syncdb
$ python manage.py checkenv # To check if everything is configured correctly
</code>
<strong>Note:</strong> Don't forget to do this after using the <strong><em>activate</em></strong> script or using
the python provided in the <strong><em>env's bin</em></strong> folder.<br/>
<strong>Note2:</strong> Create an admin user when asked or run <em>python manage.py
createsuperuser</em> later. This is used to login to the admin system.<br/>
<strong>Note3:</strong> If you are doing this on your machine, you can see the page running
by executing the command <em>"python manage.py runserver 0.0.0.0:8000"</em> and access
it in your browser with <em>localhost:8000</em>.<br/>
<strong>Note4:</strong> To disable the <strong>activate</strong> script, just run the command <strong>deactivate</strong>.</p>

<h2>Configuring Nginx and Gunicorn</h2>

<p>After you configured your mumble-django accordingly, it's time to deploy it with
gunicorn through Nginx. Let's start with Nginx config file. The location of the
file depends on your distro.
``` nginx mumble-django.conf
server {</p>

<pre><code> listen      80;
 server_name your.domain.com;
 location / {
     proxy_pass_header Server;
     proxy_set_header Host $http_host;
     proxy_redirect off;
     proxy_set_header X-Real-IP $remote_addr;
     proxy_set_header X-Scheme $scheme;
     proxy_connect_timeout 10;
     proxy_read_timeout 10;
     proxy_pass http://127.0.0.1:8888;
 }
 location /static {
     alias /home/user/virtualenv-1.9.1/MD/mumble-django/htdocs;
 }
 location /media {
     alias /home/user/virtualenv-1.9.1/MD/lib/python2.6/site-packages/django/contrib/admin/media/;
 }
 location /mumble/media {
     alias /home/user/virtualenv-1.9.1/MD/mumble-django/pyweb/mumble/media/;
 }
</code></pre>

<p>}
```
<strong>Note:</strong> You can insert this directly in <em>nginx.conf</em> file or source it from
another file, like I did using <em>mumble-django.conf</em> file.</p>

<p>Check if the configuration is ok, and if so, reload the configuration to nginx
instance.
<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ /etc/init.d/nginx configtest
</span><span class='line'>$ /etc/init.d/nginx reload</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div></p>

<p>Now we'll start the program using gunicorn. You need to go to the folder that
contains the <em>mumble-django.wsgi</em> file (At the moment, in the root of the Mumble
Django project folder).
<div class='bogus-wrapper'><notextile><figure class='code'><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class=''><span class='line'>$ cd virtualenv/MD/mumble-django
</span><span class='line'>$ ../bin/gunicorn_django -w 3 -b 127.0.0.1:8888</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure></notextile></div>
The <em>-w</em> parameter defines the number of worker processes that will serve the
requests. Use Ctrl+Z to send the process to background.
Your server should be running correctly and you should be able access it now
from your browser. It's all done.</p>

<p>Now, you could setup <a href="http://supervisord.org/"><em>supervisor</em></a> or a similar tool to manage your Mumble
Django instance. Maybe I'll write about this in the future.
Enjoy your new Murmur web front-end.</p>

<h4><em>The end</em></h4>

<!-- Link References -->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
